<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="embed">

  <copyright>
    Copyright © 2014 Mark Thomas

    Permission to use, copy, modify, distribute, and sell this
    software and its documentation for any purpose is hereby granted
    without fee, provided that the above copyright notice appear in
    all copies and that both that copyright notice and this permission
    notice appear in supporting documentation, and that the name of
    the copyright holders not be used in advertising or publicity
    pertaining to distribution of the software without specific,
    written prior permission.  The copyright holders make no
    representations about the suitability of this software for any
    purpose.  It is provided "as is" without express or implied
    warranty.

    THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO THIS
    SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND
    FITNESS, IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS BE LIABLE FOR ANY
    SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES
    WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN
    AN ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION,
    ARISING OUT OF OR IN CONNECTION WITH THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF
    THIS SOFTWARE.
  </copyright>

  <interface name="embed" version="1">
    <description summary="embed surfaces from other clients">
      The global interface for provising surface embedding capabilities.
      This is a lightweight protocol, intended for simple use cases.

      A surface may have a "hole" attached to it.  A hole has a location
      and size relative to the surface, and a uid which can be passed to
      other clients of the server over some IPC mechanism.

      A surface that is not currently in use can be plugged into a hole
      by creating a "plug" from the surface using the uid of the hole.

      Limitations.

      The two clients must collaborate to manage resizing of the buffer.
      For interactive resizes, this may not be possible without some
      delay on the embedded surface.
    </description>

    <enum name="error">
      <entry name="bad_uid" value="0"
             summary="the uid provided is invalid"/>
      <entry name="bad_surface" value="1"
             summary="the surface is invalid"/>
    </enum>

    <request name="create_hole">
      <description summary="create a hole and attach to a surface">
	Instantiates a hole object attached to a surface.

	A surface can have multiple holes, and they act
	independently.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="hole"
           summary="the new hole id"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
           summary="the surface"/>
    </request>

    <request name="create_plug">
      <description summary="plug a surface into a hole">
	Instantiates a plug object that plugs a surface into a
	hole.  If the surface is invalid, or is already in use,
	e.g. as a shell window, then the bad_surface error is
	returned.  If the uid does not correspond to a hole, the
	bad_uid error is returned.
      </description>
      <arg name="id" type="new_id" interface="plug"
           summary="the new plug id"/>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
           summary="the surface to embed"/>
      <arg name="hole" type="uint"
           summary="the uid of the hole to embed in"/>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="hole" version="1">
    <description summary="a hole to embed surfaces in">
      Represents a hole on a surface into which other surfaces can
      be embedded.
    </description>

    <request name="assign_uid">
      <description summary="assigns a uid to the hole">
	Requests that the server assigns a uid to a hole, and sends
	that uid to the client in a uid_assigned event.  Repeated
	requests will not assign new uids, but will cause new
	uid_assigned events to occur.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="uid_assigned">
      <description summary="informs the client of the hole's uid">
	Informs the client of the uid of the hole.  This is a 32-bit
	unsigned integer, which can be passed via IPC mechanisms to
	other clients of the same server.
      </description>
      <arg name="uid" type="uint"
           summary="the uid of the hole"/>
    </event>

    <request name="configure">
      <description summary="configure the location and size of the hole">
	Configures the location and requested size of the hole.  The
	embedded surface (if any) is located at the x and y co-ordinates
	relative to the parent surface.  The embedded surface plug is
	notified of the size request via a configure event, however this
	is not enforced.

	Note that changes to the size are not synchronized in the server.
	Use of the configure request during interactive or animated
	resizing may cause delayed rendering unless the two clients
	synchronize their buffer updates.
      </description>
      <arg name="x" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="y" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="width" type="uint"/>
      <arg name="height" type="uint"/>
    </request>

    <request name="remove_plug">
      <description summary="remove the plug from the hole">
	Removes the currently embedded plug from the hole.  If there
	is a plug in the hole, it is send a removed event.  If not,
	this is a no-op.
      </description>
    </request>
  </interface>

  <interface name="plug" version="1">
    <description summary="a plug which embeds a surface in a hole">
      Represents a plug which attaches a surface to another surface
      with a hole.
    </description>

    <request name="destroy" type="destructor">
      <description summary="destroy the plug, removing the surface">
	Destroys the plug, unplugging the surface from the hole.  The
	surface is unmapped if it was previously mapped.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="configure">
      <description summary="request to resize to the specified size">
	Informs the plug client what the hole's size has been set to.
	The plug client should ensure that buffers attached to the
	surface do not exceed the dimensions given.

	Note that this is not enforced, and a client could use more
	space than has been allocated to them, however this would
	overlap the hole client.
      </description>
      <arg name="width" type="int"/>
      <arg name="height" type="int"/>
    </event>

    <event name="removed">
      <description summary="the plug has been removed from the hole">
	Informs the client that the plug has been removed from the hole,
	either because the hole has requested that the plug be removed,
	or because the surface the hole was attached to has been
	destroyed.

	The plug is no longer valid after this event, and the surface
	will have been unmapped.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
